Guide to the James Jesse Strang Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
James Jesse Strang collection
1835-1920
WA MSS 447
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1
(4 boxes) + 1 folder
The collection consists of manuscripts relating to Strang's conversion to Mormonism, his relations with the Nauvoo church, his personal writings, and correspondence. The papers include accounts, drafts of patriarchal blessings, plan and diagrams for the Voree Temple, notes for sermons, lectures, debates, and material regarding the establishment of the Church of Jesus Christ (Strangite), the Order of the Illuminati, the Associated Order of Enoch, and the Kingdom of St. James. Notes and correspondence collected by Milo M. Quaife while working on The Kingdom of Saint James have been added to the papers.
Strang, James Jesse, 1813-1856
Immediate Source of Acquisition
See Description of the Papers.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
James J. Strang's "Letter Of Appointment": Restricted material. A reference surrogate has been substituted in folder 4. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Associated Materials
James Jesse Strang Papers, WA MSS S-186-189
Existence and Location of Copies
Some materials available on microfilm. Consult Public Services desk.
Scope and Contents
The James Jesse Strang Collection contains over 700 documents that trace the career of the Mormon religious leader James J. Strang. The collection includes an extensive file of incoming correspondence to Strang through 1846 and the early months of 1847, a scattering of letters through the rest of 1847 and 1848, another heavy correspondence through 1849 and the early months of 1850, and a relatively small number of letters written after Strang settled permanently at Beaver Island in the summer of 1850. With this voluminous incoming correspondence are drafts of Strang's outgoing correspondence, of roughly the same proportions as between the years though not comparable in bulk, reports of Church conferences, of individual branches, and of the "Associated Order of Enock" at Voree, letters to Strang and his wife from their relatives in New York and Illinois, documents pertaining to Strang's life before he became a Mormon, especially including his fragmentary diary, and a large miscellany.
Most of the manuscripts were brought together by Strang's son Charles. At the death of the latter they passed to Charles' brother Clement, and from him to Dr. Milo M. Quaife, who drew upon them in writing his Kingdom of St. James (New Haven, 1930). Continual additions were made to the collection over this whole long period before it was sold by Dr. Quaife. The collection includes some of Quaife's research files.
For purposes of description and facility of reference, the collection has been separated into four separate sections. Section A, The Basic Early Documents, consists of 59 lots. These include: Strang's manuscript autobiography; Strang's manuscript diary; the "Letter of Appointment," purported to have been written by Joseph Smith; testimony of high crimes committed by the Twelve; Strang's summons to the Twelve to appear for trial; Young's denunciation of Strang; Hyde's argument against Strang's claims; the plight of Joseph Smith's family in a series of letters by William Smith; Reuben Miller's description of the last days of Nauvoo; Brewster's manuscript challenge to Strang; Rigdon's downfall; Matteson's account of the Joseph Smith plates; Greenhow's expose of Taylor, Richards and Phelps; the private correspondence of General John C. Bennett; the confidential correspondence of President George J. Adams; Apostle Page's expose of the Twelve; Bennett's trial and expulsion; Strang's manuscript revelations; Brook's manuscript report on Young's tactics; and Strang's proposed appointment to the governorship of Utah Territory.
Section B, Personal Papers, comprising 100 lots, contains Strang's original draft letters writings, and family correspondence. This group helps reveal the development and difficulties of the Strangite church, the Prophet's relationship with his wives and other kin, and the wide range of ideas and effort that the leader put forth to prosper and control his flock.
Section C, The Church Archives, contains many documents, including the original manuscript papers of the Order of Illuminati, the Association Order of Enoch, the William Smith, George Adams, and other church trials, and the founding of the Kingdom of St. James with the signatures of 234 leading Mormon witnesses to the coronation proceedings.
Section D, General Correspondence, comprises upwards of 350 documents being the original contemporaneous correspondence of many of the Church notables, such as President George J. Adams (some 20 manuscripts), John C. Bennett (equally extensive), Lester Brooks, Dennis Chidester, Samuel Graham (30- odd letters), James M. Grieg, Alden Hale, Peter Hess, Lorenzo Dow Hickey, Andrew G. Jackson, Amos Lowen, William Marks, Jesse Nichols, Isaac Paden, Ebenezer Page, Stephen Post, William Smith, and Gilbert Watson.
Section E, Milo Quaife's Research Files, is material collected by Mr. Quaife in writing, The Kingdom of Saint James, (New Haven, 1930). It includes copies of articles in newspapers, some typewritten, others copied by Charles J. Strang; correspondence with Strang's descendants; notes collected by Charles J. Strang; and notes on Strang collected by Mr. Quaife.
SUMMARY DESCRIPTION OF THE STRANG MANUSCRIPTS
The following description of Strang's career and of the material in the collection comes prepared by Dale L. Morgan, who examined the papers in detail, identified the handwriting of many unsigned manuscripts, and assigned approximate dates to undated letters and documents. The period covered by the papers is from 1833 through 1856.
James Jesse Strang was born at Scipio, N. Y., March 21, 1813. His childhood, as he records in the never-complete autobiography included in these manuscripts, was sickly and unhappy, so that he was never afterwards able to look back upon it without "a creeping sensation akin to terror." He grew up without much formal education but had an active, impressionable mind which ingested learning rapidly and found play in the neighborhood lyceums and debating societies. A fragment of the diary he kept from his nineteenth to his twenty-fourth year, also in the present collection, graphically illustrates the qualities which were to make his influence so powerfully felt on the course of Mormon history. He had wide-ranging interests, an immediate sensitivity to the ideas and opinions of his times, a distinct flair for words, a liking for disputation, and above all a hunger for recognition which he united with singular tenacity of will. His diary shows also, in its occasional employment of a cipher he himself worked out, a certain liking for mystification and privacy unto himself which was to recur significantly in his later life.
Strang taught school and read for the law, being admitted to the bar of Chatauqua County in 1836. He did not, however, entertain a very high opinion of the legal profession, as his letter written to A.J. Graham in 1849 makes abundantly clear, and he varied his practice by serving as a village postmaster, temperance lecturer, and editor of a village paper. Finally, in the summer of 1843, he followed his wife's relatives to Wisconsin. Two brothers-in-law were Mormon converts, and under their influence Strang made a visit to Nauvoo early in 1844. He had once been inclined to infidelity and later had been a communicant of the Baptist church, but now he too became a Mormon, being baptized, it is said, by Joseph Smith. Whether the doctrine appealed to him or whether he saw clearly into the dynamism inherent in the new faith and joined the Church under the spur of his driving ambition still remains a fundamental enigma; his friends and relatives pondered the question at the time, and sometimes, as in the letter by Wealthy Smith, faced him with it: "What your object could have been in joining them [the Mormons], I am at a loss to know, unless it was for the sake of gain or (as I have often heard you say) to immortalize your name, for it does not seem possible that you can be a sincere believer."
The most important single document in the Strang manuscripts is the letter which launched him upon his career as prophet, seer, and revelator, the "Letter of Appointment" purportedly sent to Strang by Joseph Smith from Nauvoo on June 19, 1844, eight days before the Prophet's death. Upon the question of the authenticity of this letter Strang's integrity as a religious leader and the whole validity of his claims to lead the Church stand or fall. Under close examination the letter appears to be what the embattled Twelve Apostles branded it when first it began to stir the Church, a forgery. But it assailed Brigham Young and his associates from an unexpected quarter. The fight for the succession originally had lain between the Twelve and Sidney Rigdon, and in August, 1844, they triumphed over Rigdon by imputing to him personal ambitions which they, collectively, could not hold. "I will tell you who will lead the Church," Brigham Young roared to the Saints, "the Twelve--I at their head!" Effective as this argument had been in disposing of Rigdon, it was totally inadequate in dealing with one of Strang's tenacity and ability. To a Church which long had sung, "The Church without a Prophet is not the Church for me," Strang brought the unequivocal claim that he was the appointed and only Prophet-- selected by Joseph Smith himself--to lead them. Strang could find ample precedent in the Church law, the Doctrine and Covenants, to support his contention that the Twelve were out of their place in "usurping" the rights and duties of the First Presidency, and after a period of preparation, following his initial rebuff in the summer of 1844, he launched a smashing attack upon the position of the Twelve through the columns of the Voree Herald, which he began publishing in January, 1846.
The Strang manuscripts fully display the staggering effect of this assault upon the citadels which earlier had fallen almost by default into the hands of the Twelve. Numerous letters in the present collection, written to Strang from every quarter through the spring and summer of 1846, show how deeply disturbed many of the Saints were over the condition in which the Church found itself. Jacob Gibson spoke eloquently for many of his brethren when he wrote Strang from Philadelphia in June, 1846, that he could not fellowship the Twelveites with their false doctrines-- "Twelve Heads, ralleing for origan california Taking the gospel from the Gentiles no Proffit to Lead no Sear to disurn the Calamities &c &c."
From the viewpoint of the Twelve, no time could have been more unfortunate for a formidable claimant to the succession to take them in the flank. They were launching upon their exodus out of Nauvoo, by no means assured of finding a safe haven in the Rockies, the mob spirit growling around them in Illinois, their followers unhappy and unsettled. It was entirely possible that their following would melt away altogether. Only in the light of the Strang manuscripts can the pressures that bore upon Brigham Young as his Camp of Israel moved west across Iowa toward the distant Rockies be fully understood, or the anger and apprehension which warmed his harangues to the Saints the whole length of their journey to Utah. Moreover, Strang found immediate and able lieutenants to carry the word in person. Reuben Miller, sent by the Twelve to combat him, succumbed to his claims and personality, as he writes Strang in an important letter of February 15, 1846. Two disaffected apostles, George J. Adams and John E. Page, likewise gave in their adherence, and the smoldering feud between the Smith family and Brigham Young was productive of the conversion of William Smith, the Prophet's only surviving brother, who was soon promising to move the whole family, with all their sacred relics, to Strang's gathering place at Voree. Letters from these three men are most revelatory of their character and motives, and must have their influence in any new study of early Mormon history. Quite as important in the collection is the astonishing correspondence between John C. Bennett and Strang. Notorious for his spectacular break with Joseph Smith in the summer of 1842, when he spread about the country the most damaging stories concerning the iniquities of the Saints at Nauvoo, Bennett airily dismissed all this in his letters to Strang. It was, he said, a result of the machinations of the apostles, Willard Richards, Brigham Young, and John Taylor, who, "by a system of duplicity, fraud and corruption, succeeded in souring the mind of Joseph and producing an open rupture between us," which compelled him to fight and sustain himself "by recrimination."
Having thus shrugged off the embarrassments of his bad name, Bennett proceeded to shower Strang with ideas, suggestions, publicity notices, and deft flattery, all the while prodding Strang to offer him a potent place in his hierarchy in return for his support. With their double and triple underscorings, their "Private," and "Confidential" annotations, the Bennett letters themselves, quite apart from their content, afford a sufficiently illuminating insight into Bennett's character. Ultimately, students of Mormon history will have to write an exhaustive inquiry into Bennett's influence upon that history, from 1840 through 1860, and that study can be made only in the presence of this impressive collection of his letters.
By the summer of 1846 Strang was ready to extend his personal activities to the East. The manuscripts show how ripe was the field for the harvest. The church Sidney Rigdon had founded in opposition to the Twelve was already in process of the utter disintegration which befell it the next year. In city after city-- Cincinnati, Kirtland, Pittsburgh, Philadelphia, New York, and Boston-- the congregations fell like as many ripe plums into Strang's hand. His tour of the East was virtually a triumphal procession, and ambitious plans were on foot to send missionaries to fight for the control of the English churches and carry the gospel to the virgin terrain of the Continent. By the fall of 1846 Strang had made himself so formidable a rival as to face the Twelve with a fight to the death.
Meanwhile, however, dissension had been brewing at his home stake in Wisconsin. Under Bennett's influence, before his departure Strang had instituted a secret "Order of the Illuminati" into which the elite of the Church were initiated, binding themselves by "a great covenant" not to reveal the mysteries they were taught. Some of the Saints were offended at this "secret combination" in their midst, on the grounds that the Book of Mormon enjoined against all such; and others took umbrage at Bennett's autocratic administration and easy morals. By late summer Reuben Miller had broken with Strang's church, publishing a notable pamphlet, James J. Strang Weighed in the Balance of Truth, and Found Wanting, against his former leader, and in October Strang's insurgent brother-in-law, Aaron Smith, sat with a high council in Voree in judgment upon John C. Bennett, the astonishing and illuminating minutes of which constitute one of the most important documents in the Strang manuscripts.
Strang returned to Voree in mid-October to face open insurrection. The "anti-covenant" faction broke away entirely, publishing broadsides against him and commencing a dissenting paper. Letters in the Strang manuscripts exhibit the doubt and dismay of his followers everywhere attending this onslaught by the "Pseudoes" (pseudo-Mormons), as Strang called the dissenters; and they also exhibit the counter-measures taken by Strang and those who remained loyal. The mails brought Strang other bad news preserved in this collection, Lester Brook's sad intelligence of the utter failure of the English mission in consequence of the babbling of his fellow missionary, the celebrated Martin Harris; the rebellion of the Boston branch over the misbehavior of George J. Adams, and many other troubles. Other prophets, too, now were making their appearance, including James C. Brewster, whose circumspect inquiry to Strang early in 1846 is one of the most curious documents in the manuscripts. The Twelve also were taking steps to mend their fences, throwing overboard their earlier contention that none should ever be allowed to stand in Joseph's place and organizing a First Presidency of their own, drawn from the Quorum of the Twelve. It must have been discouraging for Strang to receive such letters as he had from George Walter, an old Missouri Saint. "cant all be right," Walter wrote him laconically, "& I hope that we are not all wrong But I am Sertainly A fraid that there is Sumthing wrong with us all if I was Axacly right I think then I could see where the wrong was but As it is I cannot tell."
Struggling manfully with schism, apostasy, unstable and unreliable aides, and the depressing poverty of his sincerest believers (the rich hung on to their wealth, as one discouraged laborer in the vineyard remarked, as though it were "expence money to Hell"), Strang endeavored with the one hand to build up a large church at Voree, and with the other to find a new gathering place. Beaver Island in Lake Michigan as early as 1846 attracted his attention, but a strange and hitherto neglected letter, unsigned, in the manuscripts, indicates that the talk about Beaver Island may have been intended as dust in the eyes of the public, with Strang's real objective being a gathering place on the islands of the St. Lawrence River. Evidently the St. Lawrence project proved not to be feasible, and finally Strang definitely decided upon Beaver Island as the place of gathering for the faithful.
The second great mission to the East, in the winter of 1849-50, which is so fascinatingly reported in the letters to and from Strang, his principal lieutenants, and the laborers in the ranks, seemingly had as its great objective the stirring up of a wave of migration to Beaver Island, where Strang was making plans to inaugurate a literal Kingdom of God. This was a mission attended by the most turbulent events, for before setting out, Strang took his first plural wife, Elvira Field, and in the guise of a young male secretary, "Charles J. Douglass," she accompanied him east. Rumors of some sexual irregularity preceded Strang from Beaver Island, and in New York, in September, he had to meet charges brought against him in the branch by one of his apostles, L.D. Hickey, and the rambunctious Increase Van Deusen, who for two years had been hawking about the New York streets a celebrated expose of Brigham Young's Nauvoo temple endowment, and who was not averse to exposing Strang in his turn. The minutes of this conference, in the present collection, show how skillfully and boldly Strang met this first ordeal. During the fall, however, persistent rumors pervaded the Strangite branches in Philadelphia and New York concerning the "physiological peculiarities" of C.J. Douglass. Strang was in no position to admit to the truth and adopted the bold course of denying nothing while standing majestically on his dignity, meantime reproaching his followers in sometimes biting language for their insinuations against his good name. The letters to and from Strang in Baltimore and the leaders of his Philadelphia branch are fascinating to read; and with them are two letters to Strang, written while he was in Washington from "Charles J. Douglass" herself, with much that may be read between the lines.
The correspondence of his missionaries to Strang during this winter of 1849-50, imposing in its proportions, shows how bitterly the battle for converts and whole congregations was still being carried on between Strang's Church and the Twelve, now securely established in Utah. Both Strangites and Brighamites regarded themselves as shepherds in whose keeping were the lambs of God, the antagonist being a wolf ravening among the flock. This struggle between the two major divisions of the original church has not heretofore been seen in proper perspective, the Strangite documents not having been available to students as have those favorable to the Utah Church. The struggle was complicated by the delicacy of the situation of the Utah Saints, who were petitioning Congress to recognize their provisional State of Deseret, and thus were anxious that no applecarts be upset. Thus D.R. Whipple writes Strang from Washington on December 28, 1849, that the day before A.W. Babbitt had come to the Strangite meeting for the first time: "after the meeting was closed he came up and told us who he was...he informed us of his being the Delegate from the Seeking to be State of Deseret. he told us that he was once a Member of the Church of the Saints but that now he was not a member of any Church yet felt an attachment to the name of Saint, he also spoke about the Church being devided and invited us to call and see him...he speaks of them [the Saints in Utah] not as Bretheren but as his Constituents." And again Whipple writes on January 9, that Babbitt "appears very anxious that we should not say or do any thing calculated in the least to hinder them in obtaining a State Government or him a Seat in Congress we have no disposition to interfere with them unless they attack You or your calling in your absence. Mr. Babbitt also informed Brother Grie[r]son that every thing pertaining to the Authority of the Church would be made perfectly Satisfactory to him."
In a position fraught with so many arresting possibilities, however, Strang could not forbear meddling. A letter from Charles Durkee, then a Wisconsin Congressman, and by interesting coincidence later a governor of Utah, addressed to Strang on January 13, 1850 a note which reveals that Strang had urged upon him the exclusion of slavery from the Territory of Deseret (Brigham Young was making the most energetic effort to keep Deseret out of the dangerous cross-fire between slavery and anti-slavery representatives in Congress, and was not likely to thank Strang for this); and among Strang's own papers in the manuscripts is a draft of a forcible statement written for the press in which he calls the State of Deseret a myth, its constitution drawn up by a mere town meeting in a single settlement of trifling size, its population insufficient to maintain a government in any regular form, and having not only no attachment to the United States but neither moral virtues nor intelligence to conduct an organized government.
Eventually the Deseret delegates failed of their objective, the Territory of Utah being created in its stead. Still another document in the Strang manuscripts is a fantastic sequel to this, a letter of March 7, 1853, by one of Strang's fellow members of the Michigan legislature commending him as a most suitable candidate "for the appointment of Governor of the new Territory of Utah," which bears out the story told in the New York Times of September 3, 1882, to the effect that Strang at one time "applied to Robert McClelland, of Michigan, who was then Secretary of the Interior in the cabinet of President Pierce, for an appointment as governor of Utah, promising that his administration should be attended by the uprooting of Brighamite Mormonism in the Salt Lake valley."